you've known Jordan Peterson since
before kind of at all of the rest of us
kind of got to know him I guess yeah it
was a strange he was a kind of strange
coincidence of events I met him in 2015
or I I heard of him in 2015 and then I I
connected with him about six months
before the whole thing started to kind
of fall apart explode and my it was
trained because when I met him when I
heard him I felt like IKEA he understood
the types of things that I was asking
myself like the types of questions about
how reality exists and about symbolism
and so when we met I felt like there was
one thing I had to tell him it was so
weird because we we right away we could
see that we could we could understand
each other and there was I just felt
like there was one message I needed to
communicate to him which was because he
talked about this notion of the monster
on the edge of the world and the idea of
the dragon and chaos kind of on the edge
of reality but III I felt like I had to
kind of tell them that that monster also
exists between categories like it so
it's not just that it exists on the edge
of something but that the world exists
in this hierarchy of levels let's say
and at the edge of each rung of the
hierarchy or also in between opposites
there is a buffer of of chaos and which
kind of protects the which both which
can both threaten but also protects the
integrity of identities right so you
need a kind of a buffer of exceptions a
buffer of things that don't quite fit on
the edges of things because that's
that's what helps you kind of like we
say the exception is the rule right it
helps you to see the identity but it it
if you're not careful it can actually
start to eat at the the identities and
so I was trying to explain like that's
what that's why we have cherubim you
know in the temple between the holy
place and the Holy of Holies in the holy
and that's why we have we have
guardians on the outside of holy places
right that act as this kind of buffer of
chaos and we talked about also the idea
of the the threshold
in a lot of cultures you're not supposed
to step on the threshold if you if you
enter someone's house you have to step
over the threshold like the step on the
threshold is that is considered a very
dangerous thing and it has to do with
this idea that there is no definite
place where the inside and the outside
of an of a house is right you couldn't
say right here like this spot where I'm
showing this is exactly the place where
the house house and the outside and
inside are because it's not something
about quantifiable it's not quantifiable
but there is a difference and so the
threshold acts as this buffer of chaos
which is neither inside or outside don't
touch it leave it alone you know let the
monster be just just step across it and
then you're on the inside and you know
you're on the inside so that's what I
kind of felt like I had to talk to him
about and Jenny was so strange that it
was that it ended up being this this
like idea of identities that aren't
quite don't quite fit into the normal
male outfield female opposite that's
what exploded on the first show exactly
and so he ended up well it's more that
the threshold started to manifest itself
like it's like the monsters which are in
a way supposed to protect the identities
such a turn on the inside has started to
devour the categories you know you see
that in a lot of stories where like I
talked about the idea of the troll in
the bridge right so the troll on the
bridge he protects he stops you from
crossing right he's there to prevent
things that aren't supposed to cross the
cross but then he can also start to give
how're things like he can start to
actually eat at those things that want
to cross over and so it's a it's like
that's the ambiguity of the of the
margin so anyway so I felt like I'd
explained that so then after that when
the Pepe thing kind of came about then I
knew that okay we need to talk about
this and then since then like I feel I
feel like Jordan he kind of he's kind of
seen me as an ally in certain things
like not everything that he does but in
certain things that he does and so he'll
call me usually very frantic you know
because he he thought of some crazy
connection and he can't you couldn't say
publicly because it would just look
insane if you just said it publicly but
you just need someone to bounce it off
and so then we'll talk it out and and so
so that's kind of been my my
relationship with Jordan
so when
you explain that thing to him was this
something he had thought of before or
was it completely new I think it's one
of those things where he hadn't thought
about it explicitly but as soon as I
said it it was like right he clicked
right away it fit right away into the
way he sees the world and and that's
kind of I think that's what happens with
symbolism to some of the things that he
says it does the same to me where I
hadn't quite thought of it in those
categories but as soon as he says it it
just kind of right away you know
intuitively that it's right and so that
was the that was kind of the
relationship that they developed right
away and then after that it felt like
that's always been kind of our
discussion is that he'll say something
then I'll say something we're both kind
of like whoa you know look like two
stoners you know kind of discovering the
the world and so it's it's it's a lot of
fun that's for sure yeah so that's how
that's and then when it happened I think
obviously when it happened to him then
it really became real you know and so he
started to see this whole idea of the of
chaos in that way as a the idea of also
this notion of deconstructing like how
post-modernism also plays a role that's
similar because that's what Jacques
Derrida
that's all he talked about was how these
indeterminate categories they can
deconstruct the categories if you play
with them in the right way they can turn
on normal opposites and-and-and actually
kind of not invalidate but like make the
normal category start to slip and then
you can't nothing nothing is stable
anymore that's good that's kind of how
we feel like things are going on right
now like the world is kind of in that
that weird space right now so I wonder
if there's some of the ambivalence that
I see and sense with Christians and
Jordan Peterson because one he doesn't
identify himself as a Christian but he's
also explaining Christian stories in a
way sort of using the psychological
mainly is there a sense that in a way
he's he's sort of potentially explaining
them away for some Christians like in a
way if you've explained them why do you
need belief and faith in the same way
how do you how do you see the the
relationship between sort of traditional
Christianity and what Jordan Peterson is
offering yeah I think I keep
thing is obviously not a Christian like
I even said like Jordan is obviously a
heretic like he's a lot of the things he
says are completely wild but I think
that I think that the way that he's
talking about things I think the way
that he's talking about about these
stories first of all it's not that new
it's it's only new it's only new for
kind of weird literalists type
Christians in the United States and in
North America especially but it but it's
not weird at all for traditional
Christians because this idea that there
are first of all different levels of
meaning in the text is very traditional
and so this notion also that the the Old
Testament is there to show us certain
moral structure than kind of ways of
interacting that can teach us lessons
about how to live our lives I mean
that's obviously very that's very
traditional I think that Jordan has
found a way to talk about it using
neuropsychology using the psychology of
attention using also evolutionary
biology that is definitely surprising
people because he's able to connect you
know research in psychology to to to how
the stories lay that some play
themselves out and I think that that's
been really fascinating for people um
and and I think what I've always said is
I think that the fact that Jordan is not
Christian is actually extremely helpful
right now because would start listening
to the media said that he was yeah
exactly it's like it's like I it's like
I I say explicitly that I'm a Christian
like it's part of my upfront identity
and because of that I know that there's
a there's a limit to how many people are
going to listen to what I'm saying I've
accepted that like it's something that I
decided to do and I've accepted it like
because he's he's a he's acting as this
weird kind of in-between figure he he
doesn't he's not threatening to people
they don't they don't feel like he's
gonna try to convert them like they they
feel like the discussion that he's
having is honest and genuine and he's
actually trying to work this stuff out
and the truth is he really is trying to
work this stuff out Jordan hasn't when
Jordan says when he doesn't answer the
question
like you believe in the resurrection of
Christ if when he doesn't answer the
question do you believe in God it's
because he's really is trying to figure
it out for himself he's not he's not
it's not a it's not a theater move that
he's doing like he he you know I had up
I had a discussion with Jordan just a
few weeks ago where he he called me and
we started talking about about Genesis
again and attention and this hierarchy
of attention and everything and how how
God gathering the dust and blowing his
spirit into the dust is the same
structure as how we basically encounter
the world like we gather in this
potentiality then we infuse meaning into
it and he was like and then he said
something he said he said Oh said it's
so terrifying to think that these
stories could actually be true like what
do you mean what do you mean it's it's
terrifying he said well what do we do
what do we do if they're true you know
and so it's like Jordan is actually he
actually is working through this stuff
he's not pretending and I think that's
one of the reasons why people have been
so genuinely interested in what he's
saying he's no different in private than
he is in public like this is what's
happening I think that the Christians
most of the Christians that I've reacted
negatively to him have been the kind of
Calvinist types that the kind of the
more rigid are you saved
are you not saved like that kind of
Christian I think they're the ones who
have been reacting more to him I think
that most other people have just
accepted that he personally he's not a
Christian he's not saying he's a
Christian and and he's just there I
always talk about him as as a kind of uh
as a transitional figure he said I
always say that he's like King Cyrus
King Cyrus in the Bible he he's the one
who sent the Israelites back to build
their temple like he wasn't any is he
wasn't in his real light he didn't
believe in God like he he had all these
idols and he and he he was he was a man
of you know a powerful man but because
he he was a then because of that he was
the one who was able to say like hey you
know why don't you go back in that
temple that you had you know it's
there's something interesting there was
it interesting you you should do that
you should go back like go back to your
thing and because of that there have
been I mean I've been witnessing to
myself like there are thousands of
people that are going
to church like at least at least
hundreds of people have written me
personally emails talking about how
they're kind of rediscovering their
Christian faith at a different level
they kind of move past the the 13 year
old version of Christianity and they
discovered something more more powerful
and I keep telling them like that's what
Christianity is it's all that's always
what it's been maybe not obviously not
the evolutionary biology so because they
didn't talk about that stuff but the
notion that these that these stories
manifest these ways of being and these
these manners of encountering the world
and that it has to do with consciousness
and has to do with our or our experience
of the world like that there's no
mystery like that's really what what
it's about you know so you can you can
easily go back to church and then and
then discover that now it doesn't mean
that when you go back to church you're
only going to encounter people who who
understand that religion is a hierarchy
like the way it's set up is the
hierarchy it's it's there the way the
stories are told there they're supposed
to be able to engage and touch the
dumbest peasant right and at the same
time engage and touch the scholar the
the scholar of religion the philosopher
okay but you can't expect everybody to
have the same level of understanding so
if you go to a church you're going to
encounter someone who has a very direct
very literal very kind of in-your-face
vision of what those stories are about
and you shouldn't be surprised about
that
because that's for everybody to fit it's
like the saying the sam harris version
of religion he would be able to
enlighten everybody so that everybody
understood the higher meaning of
religion and nobody was attached to
their like the kind of more immediate
lower version of of a believing stuff
and it's like that's not gonna happen
some people are never going to reach
that some people are never going to
reach that level it's impossible you the
reason we're talking is you go in touch
with me to talk about organized religion
which is a subject I'm really interested
to hear your thoughts it's a kind of a
common the kind of common story for the
last few generations in the West I grew
up in a Protestant kind of Baptist
background very very conservative I
would say like a you know conservative
thinking a lot of creationism all that
stuff
luckily my father was a very intelligent
person he was a pastor actually for a
part of my youth and he was very he's
very curious and very intelligent person
you always encourage inquiry and
encourage deeper thinking so the the
whatever fundamentalism I was getting
was mostly getting it from my
surrounding not not necessarily for my
family but I kind of had to say in
university I started asking a lot of
questions and I started seeing the
limits let's say of where I was coming
from and I started to discover the same
as you I started to read texts from
Eastern traditions from read more you
know kind of Gnostic type text and I
thought okay what I could understand
what they're talking about like what
they're talking about this this
transformation of the person that
salvation the way was presented to me as
a as a child that's there as a young
person was you believe in Jesus right
you leave in Jesus and then you're saved
so it was like believe in Jesus and you
get this ticket you know you die you go
to heaven like yeah I then I read the
Mystics and I realize okay that's not
what it's about but that's not exactly
what it's talking about it is talking
about this transformation of the person
and the notion of ascending into heaven
it is it's a transformation of the
person to become to be free from the
let's say the things that hold us down
like our passions and and you know our
belly and all those things that kind of
hold us back and our thoughts all of
that needs to kind of to fall away and
then to enter into that silence let's
say that the inner silence and the this
uh this transcendent place that we can
find in our heart and that God can
interact with us so I was like okay
that's awesome and but at first I
thought at first I thought okay well why
is it that it doesn't why is it that I
find this in reading you know Hindu
texts or reading Gnostic texts or
reading kind of weird weird text but
it's not in Christianity why you know
why is that the case and then I realized
that it was in Christianity it's just
that no one had ever taught me those
those traditions and then I discovered
the church father
and I discovered the the mystical
Christian tradition hesychasm
especially the the tradition of the east
that's when I discovered st. gregory of
nyssa and some maximus the confessor and
gregory palamas this whole line of
mystical teachers that that are in the
Orthodox tradition and that led me
finally to convert to orthodoxy where
everything is seen through that mystical
lens and so the whole purpose of
everything we do even all the rules that
we have they're not just simple moral
rules of you should do this you
shouldn't do that but they're they're
just basically tools to help you move
into your heart and encounter Christ and
be illuminated by Christ and so that was
kind of my my past and in that I
discovered the symbolic language and and
how the symbolic language had to do with
this notion of I talked about kind of
entering the heart in terms of a person
but you can do that in terms of of your
experience of the world so the world
actually comes together and starts to
shine like things start to be brighter
than they were before as you see things
come together in in in the logo so you
could say like I think people who are
listening to you will now start to know
with that that means it's not just
gobbledygook right and so that that's
kind of what led me to to where I am and
so for me the discovery for me in terms
of organized religion I think that in
order for all the levels to be stacked
up properly you know because you one of
the things that is still accessible to
most people today is this idea of the
personal mystical experience right but
the difficulty with that personal
mystical experience is that if it's
proper right it also has to to stack at
the the next level and it also has to
bring communities together
ready can't just be on an individual
level because it it has to line up with
the way the world exists and so if you
if you if you start to have let's say
intuitions mystical intuitions or you
start to have that process of getting
rid of these passions that you have and
kind of
moving in then that also needs to happen
at the communal level and then it has to
have it it has to have a social
equivalent or else it's not real it's
not totally real so I think that that's
why for me in the end there had to be a
religious aspect to it religious and
really in the sense of a place where you
go and you are in communion with other
people the same way that you're able to
commune your thoughts together in your
heart you have to rep that has to happen
again at a social level and ideally it
has to happen at a kind of universal
level where those churches also are
communion with other churches and that
kind of creates this body which is in
Christianity called the body of Christ
it's kind of this this cosmic body you
could say where everything kind of comes
together and so it's like I think that
we can do that we can kind of engage in
in Christianity in the body of Christ
without being naive right without being
naive in not understanding that just
like in myself I have all these things
pulling me in all these directions that
I have all these crazy thoughts that I
have all these crazy desires that I have
different personalities sometimes it
manifests themselves and I start to act
in these weird patterns so - on a social
level you have the same problem you have
perversions that set themselves up you
have power struggles etcetera something
all this stuff happens at at the church
level and so I think it's it's incumbent
on us not to be naive about it not also
to just accept it but also not to be
scandalized by the fact that that
happened because if it happens in me
it's gonna happen at the other level -
like I'm not I'm not you know I'm not
fully illuminated let's say I don't know
if that makes sense yeah I I feel the
first bit you were saying about sort of
the transformational aspect of of the
experience is something I resonate with
because I've done a lot of personal
growth work which I now feel like I
understand at a deeper level because I'm
now framing it within okay the more I
speak my I speak my truth the more align
myself with the logos the more the more
I simplify my being in some way the more
I kind of have this and able to live
that out in my own life and I mean
able to frame a lot of the work that
I've done which was probably offered
more within a new agey kind of framework
within a slightly deeper cut much deeper
Christian framework yeah but I also Paul
Van de clay said that you were quite
skeptical about Jung because because I
would say Jung maps on to that sort of
transformational aspect of of growth and
and religious experience I think you
know it's weird I keep telling you I
haven't really read Jung that much like
I've read a little bit of Jung that
everybody's read when they're in college
or whatever like I haven't really
studied Jung very much I think that the
reason why I hadn't I had never studied
Jung is that I feel like he he he makes
what he Key's kind of like Jordan it's
worried because I it's like it's like I
like Jordan because I know him and we
like he comes up to the psychological
level and then he kind of stopped there
but maybe I'm wrong that's the feeling
that I get is that I feel like the step
after Jung is to realize that that is
really how reality is in an objective
way that is like you know you see for
example Jordan does this thing like he
did this thing this I'm here debates
where he talks about the spirit of the
father coming up like this notion of the
Spirit of the father being kind of
elected by the people who elect to hide
the sense of the leader and then that
keeps going and going going and that
comes up and then we have this image of
the Father and heaven right and then
it's like that's it that's yeah that's
right that's right that's right but then
at some point you have to realize it
that's the reason why that happened
because that's actually the shape of
reality like you were not we're not
separate from reality okay we're not
separate from that process like that
process it in order to for it to to have
happened in - to persist like it has to
manifest something about the real world
like it has to manifest something about
about how reality is structure and so
then for me it's like then you can to me
it's not a then it becomes not a problem
to say I can say my father our Father
who is in heaven and I and I can just
say that I don't have to do all the
psychological work behind
like I don't have to kind of convince
myself about all these steps about how
the spirit of the father merged out of
all these different that it's like I can
just say our Father was in heaven and I
know that that's the truest way to
encounter the the infinite power let's
say the the the infinity of of
generation of the of the infinite
generating person and I can I can say
that so to me it's I always felt like
young kind of stopped there and I think
that one of the problems I had with
young too is I think I felt like he was
it's not his fault totally he was in the
19th century early 20th century occult
like the kind of occult thinking where
it was really it was that strong sense
of Christians got it wrong Christians
didn't understand what they were doing
it's like here I'm gonna show you like
what it really was and also that's why I
kind of get hung up on Gnosticism it's
like you'll know so did that she was
like oh the Gnostics got it right the
Christians got it wrong and then here we
are you know poor us we where like if
the Gnostics had had one like we'd be so
more in light so much more enlightened
think that that I think that's that's
that's the wrong way to go about it and
I think that it's subversive in the end
that it actually ends up I think that
young in in the manner to which he acted
that way he he participated in the the
fragmentation of the social fabric let's
say of the West in in trying to because
we see it if you want to know the way to
destroy Christianity we've seen it
happen in the past 10 years where every
year there's some new weird fragment of
text that they find in the desert and
then they tell us here's this new
fragment like it's revealing us the real
truth about about Jesus that we've
ignored for the past thousand years
if only we had had this this weird
fragment that we found somewhere in
underground in the desert like we would
now have the all the wisdom and and I
think that that's a that's a subversive
element it's really there to constantly
break apart what the could the social
cohesion so that's that says that was my
problem with young but you know III had
to be fair like I haven't read
I haven't read enough young to to be and
that's why I haven't actually never I've
never been openly critical about you
neither I've always kind of distanced
myself from him but I'd never been
openly critical about him because I
don't know enough about him to to really
be able to say even I probably what I've
already said
might be wrong because I know what I
know for secondary sources and stuff I
guess you're you're saying it's kind of
all was like explaining Christianity
away and rather than explaining
Christianity that is that your sense I
know I would i I don't know if it's
explaining it away it's like I think
it's it's it's um
you know a it's a kind of it's a kind of
sign it I don't know if it's a kind of
sign to somebody it's a kind of it's a
kind of manner to say that reductionism
if we can find the psychological
mechanisms by which these things happen
then we don't need the the metaphysical
let's say instead of seeing that the
psychological structure is manifesting
the structure of reality right it's it's
it's it's mirroring the structure of
reality so reductionism would be a
better maybe that's a way to see it yeah
maybe that would be a way to say it
which is sort of what the materialist
day by saying well it's just it's just
chemicals what it's just by it's just it
so that's what there's no need for the
word just in that like yes it is
chemicals but how is that not
necessarily representing another reality
or another reality and that all of these
realities are stacked its other gamma
it's a judgment of what you're making
your primary lens and then assuming
everything else is is should be seen
through that lens rather than saying
well there are multiple levels and there
and things are manifesting at all of
them yeah because we don't we don't
experience love as a bunch of chemicals
in our brain if you do yeah like it's
you in trouble we experience love in the
realm of language and consciousness and
relationship and and and and if you try
to reduce that to the chemicals in your
brain you're not doing justice to the
experience of that you're you're and and
you know I I think that that if it
brings us back to the discussion about
Sam Harris a we had that we had before
where there's a there's a podcast where
he talked with it I forget who it was
yet a podcast about this notion of house
reality stacks like how you know
emergent they call emergent phenomena
right how how things come together into
identities right at higher
because it's not just a quantum field
like we don't just experience it but in
the end it is just a quantum field right
it is just in terms of material
substrate it's just a quantum field and
so but then how do these different
levels of reality stack on each other
and Sam kept wanting to he's kept saying
I want to explain it with the lowest
common possible thing but that doesn't
make sense because you know like
millions and billions like there's
millions of atoms in your hand and
there's no point in explaining it with
those millions of atoms instead of
explaining it with the deer like I'm
thirsty I'm going to drink a glass of
water explaining it through the realm of
consciousness and I think that that's
yeah that's that's that's the thing is
that just because you find the material
causes of something does it mean that
you've eliminated the higher realities I
think I think it's to me it's so obvious
but I guess a lot of people aren't able
to see it but it to me it's so obvious
like I can both say that the music that
I like comes from my my iPod you know
but also comes from I don't know like
Kanye West or whatever like it and and I
can also say that Kanye West is
manifesting you know certain immutable
patterns of relationships that make it
so that I can like that music and so
it's like I don't have to eliminate I
don't have to say well I know I
discovered the secret of music it's
coming from my earphones I've got I've
got it
you dumb people who think the music
particles exactly it's like so you dumb
people who think that music has meaning
it's like it's all moving particles yeah
I could just imagine a music review page
that was just like every single every
single album was it's just moving
particles different way to the other
ones exactly and it's and certain
chemicals in your brain have been we
were able to see which section in your
brain doesn't is is is active yeah the
problem is that that's what you find I
mean that's what you find in at least a
lot of the people that I've encountered
that are so against religion you know
they say things like God doesn't exist
and and I think well you know what if
you think that exists
means that you can hold it in your hand
you can touch it and feel it then yes
God doesn't exist
fine I'm totally fine with that like if
you think that if you even if you think
that it means that you can contain it
even conceptually then yeah God doesn't
exist right because God the whole idea
of God in the in the Christian tradition
and in all the monotheistic traditions
is that God is uncontainable that God is
beyond all concept all name all
representation and that not that the
representations are arbitrary that they
help you to kind of get closer to to the
to the mystery but that but that that
God is not a thing right and so it's
really hard to argue with an atheist who
wants you to prove that God exists like
he wants you like he wants you to prove
that you know that that that tree has
fallen in the forest like you can't it's
not the same kind of proof
even existentialism starts from that
perspective of realizing the language we
are using cannot encapsulate the thing
we're trying to explain yeah this is
everything by definition language is
going to be a subset of it any
representation of everything is going to
be a subset of everything yeah therefore
it cannot it cannot be articulated yeah
but I think that the proper way to see
it at least at least like in it from the
Orthodox perspective we have this idea
we have these two visions of theology
when it's called apophatic theology and
catyph Attic theology an apathetic
theology means this denial right this
saying that that that God is beyond all
name all definition right that you
cannot encompass the divine in in
language and images and whatever but
then the other aspect is that because of
that everything actually does manifest
the divine right so one of the problems
people have one of the problems we've
seen in post-modernism especially is
that they'll have this apathetic move
well they'll say something like you
can't represent reality reality is
beyond our capacity to represent it and
then they make this weird move where
they say therefore it's all arbitrary
right all their structures are arbitrary
our social structures are constructed
they're all arbitrary but that's not the
red move the red move is then to see
that actually all of reality then flow
out of that mystery and actually points
in a very fragmented way but points
towards that unsaid mystery and so
that's what lays out the hierarchy right
that's what lays out the hierarchy of
being is is both those moves where you
say it's something beyond but then
everything is manifesting that beyond
and it's kind of its kind of flowing out
of it and that that that's what helps
that it helps avoid it helps avoid the
absurd aspect of existentialism in my in
my opinion at least I'd love to ask you
because I heard the interviewed Paul van
der clay recently and he he said
something along these lines I think
after the interview that it all comes
down to the resurrection that and I
think he may have sent me a quote I may
have seen a quote that said if the
resurrection didn't happen then every
Christian is a fool or something like
that do you want do you understand what
that means from a from a theological
perspective I mean yeah I think I think
therefore sure that the Christianity
hinges on the resurrection hmm I think
that's for sure
I I I think that how can I say this I
keep telling people to be a little bit
careful when people think that they know
what the resurrection is I don't think
it's that easy to to know what the
resurrection is I always tell people I
believe the resurrection is an event and
I and and I think that the text
describes that event both in a very
experiential way that the people who
were there experienced experience the
resurrection in an in a very extreme way
the tomb was empty you know there were
these encounters but it's it's also not
that simple it's not as because people
people think that the resurrection just
means a dead body sitting up and walking
out like that's not how it's described
in the text Christ hides himself in the
resurrection so after the resurrection
Christ manifests himself to to these
people and they don't recognize him and
it takes a long time before they
actually recognize Christ in his
resurrection and so I think that that
that in the story it's important to see
that it was deliberately put in the
story that whatever the resurrection is
is not is not obvious it's not an
obvious thing and and sometimes people
who want to reduce the resurrection to
some kind of some kind of resuscitation
right like some kind of someone passing
out and you do CPR on them and then they
sit up in the Nick off out you know
their whether it's in their lungs or
whatever like I think that that is an it
is a very that's a very naive way of
seeing it and some people can see it
that way it's fine but I think that we
shouldn't reduce it to that we should be
careful not to reduce it to that but I
do agree that the resurrection is the
hinge of Christianity and the
resurrection has to do with the idea
that the world is essentially can
participate in God that's what the
resurrection means direction means that
the created world the manifest world the
the world of phenomena can embody can be
a house for the infinite and can
manifest the infinite and so it redeems
the world right it makes the world
participate in in in divinity and so if
you look at the the last image in the in
in Revelations like you follow the whole
story
the last image in Revelations I think I
keep telling people that's the image to
you help you to see what the result of
the resurrection is in the end and it's
this it's the the New Jerusalem the
heavenly Jerusalem and what it is it's a
it's a garden in the middle the Garden
of Eden in the middle and then the city
around it and the city is made glorious
right it's gold and jewels and
everything so it's it's represented in a
glorious manner and so both the natural
world the natural world contained but
then also all of human activity all of
technology all of human knowledge all of
the extra building that that
consciousness can do and the body right
the the the actual physical world can be
can participate can be can be
transformed can be full of light right
can can be transfigured how I don't know
how else you want to say and so and so
that that has repercussions which go
beyond which go beyond our our very
immediate experience of the world like
how does that link to the mystical
experience because what you're
describing is a mystical experience it's
the same thing it's exactly the same
thing so if you look at the same
resurrection the idea that the mystical
experience of oneness transcendence kind
of the world glowing from within
interacts with the world in a real way
that's right it's exactly what it is and
that's exactly what it is it so when you
when you read the the Saint when you
read several of the mystics they talk
about how the resurrection is accessible
already that we can already participate
in the resurrection of the body that
it's not that it is something which is
at the end right and it's important that
it's at the end because it encompasses
everything and so it happens at the end
of the world
at the end of history at the end of you
know time whatever you want to say
because it is the final thing it's the
thing that encompasses everything so you
could see it as encompassing the whole
world but you can see it also as
encompassing all of time and so that's
why it's important that it's represented
eschatologically that it's represented
in the future in the final revelation
let's say but what it is the cosmic
participation in the the mystics
experience it is a cosmic version of
what the mystic experiences in his
illumination and that's exactly what it
is in that in and I could say that
without a hint of worry that any at
least orthodox theologian is gonna come
in and slap me on the wrist because
that's really what what what it is it
also sounds pretty psychedelic
I don't know I'm not I've never done
psychedelic so I don't I I know or the
the the traditional versions of this so
I don't know about the psychedelic one
I'm just I guess I've discovered like
this world is psychedelic with Jordan he
always kind of sometimes he kind of
freaks me out when he when he thought he
tells me things like he's I had this
vision and he told me his vision it's
funny because his visions are always
quite coherent simple
luckily you know and so I can I can't a
like oh it's connected to this is this
like you can show them what it's
connected to
but it's just funny to think that
they're due to mushroom so it's gonna
kind of like it's weird was the was
there anything that we we haven't
discussed yet you'd like to to cover I
don't know I I think I maybe I'd like to
kind of hear your take or your vision
let's say of what are the challenges or
the the opportunities of organized
religion like what do you think are the
problems and what you think or how could
you see it at negative and positive
terms let's say I mean it's clear that
the the absence of a space and a reason
to to come together is is something
that's really we're really lacking in
society a friend of mine created
something called Sunday assembly
I don't know if you've heard about it's
a it was an atheist church or is an
atheist Church so he's a stand-up comic
and together with another stand-up comic
friend of that his they they was like
well why do why do only people come
together for religious things why can't
we create this is an atheist Church and
the interesting thing is like I don't
think I'm speaking out of turn for him
here is that they they created as an
atheist church and it's become more and
more spiritual as times gone on like
they've it's developed its own kind of
they realized how insufficient atheism
was as a kind of organizing principle
for a community to come together right
and it sort of developed a little bit
more of a kind of spiritual tone as
times gone on but I certainly feel in
myself that that lack of an organizing
principle and that just there's also
something about like I went to Paul van
der clays service in sacramento quite
recently what I realized is my think
this is something to do with our
tribalism we need we need a context to
be able to let our guard down there's a
sense that when we all go to church
together
because we all tacitly acknowledge that
we have the same value system but we
have the same objectives that we have
for the same reason it allows you to
talk to anyone there like you
immediately drop the bat drop the
barriers where there's all in pretty
much every other social situation apart
from maybe a festival like a really good
festival and not that doesn't always
happen we always have these boundaries
between us and them we need something to
allow us to to connect with others we
need an excuse so we need a context so
that's what I think for me that's what I
realized when I went to Paul's church
was oh okay wherever you come from you
can go into one of maybe an AAA meeting
might give you the same experience like
we all we need this shared context to be
able to get over our our yeah our innate
tribalism I think and that's what for me
I recognized and I don't know whether
it's possible to have that without I
think you'd have to have a religious
framework of some kind for that or a
shared a shared value system of some
kind I don't know whether you're sort of
suggesting that we need a renewal of
traditional Christianity or traditional
religion and I I kind have some sympathy
with that but I also have a sense that
probably for my generation and younger
if there is something that that kind of
fills that spiritual void that we're all
feeling that it's probably going to look
somewhat different from from what we've
seen before
hmm yeah I mean it'll be interesting to
see how yeah how how it works out I kind
of I think that I kind of see it in the
long in a long term like I see it in a
long story and so I already see let's
say to me that the the Reformation for
me was already kind of a problem in
terms of what it did to the west it's
like I think we're the product of this
kind of breakdown I think one of the
difficulties is when when the highest
value that is that a society has turned
towards when that starts to change like
tries to fragment you can maybe hold on
to the you can maybe hold on to the
smaller communities because we still we
have those small communities right I
mean
we have you kids like you said it could
be an a a meeting it could just be a
knitting group it could be an old ladies
who go get together to knit right they
have a common thing which unites them
and makes them into a little community
and I but I think that in order for
larger in order for like that say all of
society to have some form of capacity to
interact there need we needs to agree on
the highest let's say or at least work
as hard as possible to agree on the
highest and I think that that's what I
think that's what the church offered
let's say the West for you know like a
thousand years let's say and and it was
actually the only thing like in Western
Europe was Western Europe was so dark
and so convoluted and there was all
these wars and all these barbarians
coming down and everything the only
thing that made it even to something
like that made it somehow one was the
was was the fact that we could at least
all kind of agree you know this is what
we're aiming to you know then the
Incarnation is at least what we aim
towards so I think that I mean it's
probably idealistic for me to think that
that's what we would need like something
that's why I tended to to return to to
more traditional Christianity but it's
we're in a difficult situation for sure
i I think I fear I think I fear that
those smaller communities that we that
there's going to happen it's gonna
happen again like it happened in in the
20th century hopefully not as bad but
that's what nationalism was right we
can't agree on the highest on the
highest unity and so are the one we can
find that solid is our national identity
so we kind of clumped around our
national identities and then we had
these crazy wars that you know that were
there were nuts and so I feel like in
the wake of World War Two as we you know
it's just been two generations I was
said like the last one the last veteran
of World War two dies the last people
that survived World War two
it's gonna happen again because we
haven't dealt with anything we haven't
dealt with any of the questions that
were being posed at that time so I think
I have the same sense it's like also
some Sun lessons after we learn the hard
way like if you gotta have a lived
experience of how bad things can get
then it's very difficult to kind of even
even think or articulate it to yourself
yeah well let's hope let's hope cuz this
one this this turn is gonna have
artificial intelligence in it think
about it too much I think that to me I
think that that participating in
something which has the possibility of
of kind of uniting things together I
think to me that's been my drive back
towards traditional Christianity so but
I mean like I'm Orthodox I'm not
Catholic so I'm also somehow
participating in this weird this weird
kind of fragmentation you know like at
the same time I feel like there's a lot
of things in Catholicism which are which
are off and so and I think orthodoxy has
more of that mystical vision that I that
I did I think is important to have as
the central core like if you you have
the mystical vision as a central core
then then the world flows out you know
in them in a more ordered way I think